Hey everybody, welcome to another
content video going over pandas,
data frames, and how to use
them. So this content video we're
going to talk about lock and
ilock as well as at and iat which
are buried somewhere in the
section 7.142. So I would
just kind of like go to
that section and then just
scroll till you see it or
you can do a control find.
So in the last content video we We
talked about how data frames do allow
you to index with the brackets,
but it's not the best way to do it.
So, Panda's documentation recommends
using lock and ilock, at and
iat, which, as it says here, are
optimized to access data frames
and also give you more possibilities
beyond the brackets. I'm
just reading the textbook, but
we're going to summarize more than
the textbook gives us here. So,
what we're going to need to do
is let's jump over to, hang on,
I think this is the wrong file.
Give me just a second.
Okay, we got the right file here.
This is going to be our,
let's add a markdown
cell, our lock and ilock,
as well as at and iat.
LOCK stands for location, and
ILOCK stands for index location.
Same with AT. AT just is
kind of like another lookup
and IAT is an additional way
to look up. So let's start by
importing pandas, which is our
favorite thing. And then we'll
make a data frame, base it
off of the Titanic data set.
We'll grab that data set again.
There it is. And just to make
sure we've got it coming in right,
we'll output the first five rows
and looks good. Okay, perfect.
So first thing that
we're going to want to do
when we're using lock and
ilock is set an index.
And what I mean by that is that
by default, your data frame will
have an index. It's just going to
start at zero and go to however
many entries you have in your
data frame. But sometimes it's
nice if we have one that is more
intentional. So, for example,
let's say data frame, let's
name it data frame named.
Let's set it equal to our
data frame. We'll set index.
Index.
And let's actually use the
name column to set the index.
Here's what I mean by that.
Take a look at this data frame that I
have up above versus this data frame.
So you can see that now instead of just
having an arbitrary zero to whatever,
our index is more intentional. It's
indexed by their name. So if you
wanted to look somebody up, you
could do it by the name attribute.
And this will be nice because
now we can use, well, we could
have used our dot lock attribute
before but now we can grab
specific names from our data
frame using the lock attribute.
So let's grab Mr. Owen Harris
here for example with the lock
attribute. So what this returns
to us is all the data or all
the information on that same
row as Mr. Owen Harris-Brand.
It's got his passenger ID, his
survival, he did not survive,
his class, his sex, his age, his
siblings or spouse, his parent or
child, his ticket number, his fare,
his cabin number, and what port
he embarked from. And then also
at the bottom it's got his name.
We could also grab a subset of
this. So let's add another code
cell. I'm going to grab this code
and then what I want to do is
I want to not just grab his
name but I also well actually I
guess I just want to grab a subset
of this data let's see grab his
survival rate and his class and
his age and if I was to output
this you can see that I'm subsetting
the data in a very similar
way to how we were doing it
before. It's just that this time
I'm using the lock attribute
instead of just brackets to index.
You could also index with a slice,
so if I wanted my data a frame at,
whoops,
let's get it from, we'll take Mr. Harris
again, and then let's
slice to this person.
And we could even take it a step further
and we could grab just their sex.
and their age or sorry we
could grab their sex and slice
it to their age and then we
could output this oops second
here
you know what I forgot to do dot
lock that will be that would be why
okay there we go the whole thing
I'm teaching and I forgot to do
it okay so here we have a slice
of the rows and a slice of the
columns so you could really see how
this could be really helpful with
finding specific values. And then
on the flip side, we've got iLock,
which does the same thing, except we just
use an index instead.
So if I say data frame,
iLock, and let's give it,
I don't know, zero to four.
Here you can see the first
four rows of my data frame.
Now one thing to note with
iLock is that it is inclusive.
I know it's so hard to remember
which like range isn't inclusive but
like random.rand int is inclusive
and then the iLock is inclusive
but just a data frame with regular
brackets for indexing isn't
inclusive. So I mean when in doubt
just print it out that's what I say.
We could also
do a similar slice where we maybe
get the zero width column, or maybe
that's the zero width row, I can't
remember. And let's get a slice of,
oh, I don't know, there's one to four.
Let's see. So that is a single
row, but four columns. Okay, so
yeah, this is similar slicing,
So I guess row column is how it
how it slices. So we've got the
name, the class, survival rate,
and we could continue
with different slices like
this. So I mean if we
wanted to go really crazy,
we could view a slice of the
rows and a slice of the columns.
Let's get the zero with the
second and fourth column.
We've got passenger ID, their
class, their sex, and only
three rows of them. So So very
exciting information, I know.
But this just helps us to
subset our data so that we can
use our data frames in the
way we want. We can pull the
data out that we want. We can
take a closer look at things.
All sorts of options here.
So at and I at are going
to be slightly different.
They're supposed to be the
quickest way to pull out one
element. So for example, if
I want a data frame, whoops.
named, and we'll do dot at,
and then let's get that one name, yeah.
I really wanted to know
this specific name.
I could also throw in, let's
grab her, I don't know, her fare.
you can see that she paid 53
I don't remember that dollar
or something like that we could
do the same with I at let's
grab the zero with row this
column that would give us
another float here so the at
and I are again they're supposed
to be faster so that you can
pull out specific elements
usually just one is what you're
going to be looking for with at
and I at you're just looking
for one location or one specific
element at one spot I guess whereas
lock and I lock are going to
be able to give you more elements
than that so that's going to
sum up everything for this content
video thank you for watching